All right. So, we are back here on our
index.html page that we've been working
on. So, what I'm going to do is I'm
going to delete all of our variables
that we created here and I'm just going
to show you well, we'll maybe leave our
first name. So, I'm just going to leave
the first name variable and I'm going to
show you the first type of output. So,
this output you've probably seen on a
website before. It shows a little popup
at the top. Um, and so we're going to
use a little bit of built-in
functionality with JavaScript and we're
going to display that message. So, the
way you display a message in JavaScript
that you want to pop up on someone's
screen is you use the keyword alert. And
you should see it will come up with this
little box. If it's not highlighted, the
box will be purple. Um, so we'll say
alert. And then I'm going to put an
opening parenthesy. When I do that,
Visual Studio Code automatically closes
it. And it gives me this little message
right here. And it says alert. And then
in between the parenthesis, it's has
something that says message with a
question mark, a colon, and then the
word any. So what that's telling us is
that in between these parenthesis, I can
put a message. This is the message
that's going to display on the screen.
What type of variable can I put here?
Well, it can be anything. So um I could
put in a string. I could put in an
integer. I could put in a boolean. It
doesn't really care, but it will take in
a message. So let's put in a message
here. So, I could say this is a
programming course. We are required to
start with hello world. So, we're going
to say hello world. And then I'm going
to save that.
Um, if we open up our website by
clicking the go live button or just tab
over, you can see that we now have this
pop-up in the center of our screen or if
you're using a different web browser
than Safari, it might be somewhere else,
but you'll get a popup that says hello
world. Um, I can close it. And if we
reload the page, we get our pop-up again
that says hello world. And this happens
because we've written an alert function
that says show a message on this page.
The message we want to show is hello
world.
This alert function takes in input. So
from the keyboard from the user, so
instead of hard coding in the text hello
world, we could pass in the variable
name first name. And now if we save it
and we come back to our page, now the
alert box says Toa. And then when we hit
close, we come to our web page. So
that's how you do an alert box. Alert
boxes are great for showing messages to
users. Sometimes you want to show a
message that's not designed for the
users to see, but maybe if they're
digging into the problem on their on the
website, maybe it's not loading and
they're a little techsavvy, they might
open the developer tools. So maybe you
want to send a message that's just for
developers. So the way that we do that
is instead of using alert, we'll use a
different built-in piece of
functionality in JavaScript. This one is
called console.log. So you'll type the
word console and you'll hit tab if
you're autocompleting and then you'll
type dot and then this is all of the
things that you could do with a console.
But in our case, we're just going to use
log. We're gonna put an opening
parenthesy and it says it can take in a
data just a piece of data and it will
and that data can be any type. So
similar to the alert it can take in any
piece of data and it can be any type. So
it can be a string, an integer, float, a
boolean, you name it, you can put it in
console.log. So, I'm going to once again
type hello world here and I'll save it
by hitting command S or if you're on a
Windows, hit control S. You'll notice my
dot up here at the top vanished. If we
go back over to our web page, the alert
box didn't show up because we got rid of
that. But if I click on the console tab
here, um you can see down at the bottom
it says hello world. So, if you've been
following along and you enabled your
developer tools or if you were on a
Windows, if you've opened up your
developer tools, you can see this hello
world message here. But the average user
who doesn't have their developer tools
open won't see that message at all. So,
that's the benefit of console.log. It's
great for when you're trying to debug
something on your site. You can show
test messages there and then take them
out before you show it to the user. Um,
but that should cover our two outputs.
So, the first output is alert, second
output is console.log, log. And that
will wrap up this